Finding aid to the Gladys Eugenia Bryson Papers CA.MS.00338
Smith College Archives
Gladys Eugenia Bryson Papers
1897-1953
Smith College Archives
Bryson, Gladys Eugenia, 1894-1952
CA.MS.00338
1.333 linear feet (3 containers)
Professor and chairman of the Sociology Department. Collection contains correspondence, obituaries, clippings, class notes, exams, articles, and photographs.
Biographical / Historical
Gladys Eugenia Bryson was born in Carlisle, Kentucky on April 2, 1894. After receiving a B.A. from Georgetown College in Kentucky, Bryson obtained her M.A. in 1927 and her Ph.D. in 1930, both from the University of California at Berkeley. As the national secretary of the Y.W.C.A.'s student council, one of its national boards, Bryson served the organization from 1919-1925. For the next two years, she was a teaching fellow in the Department of Sociology and Social Institutions at Berkeley, as well as an active member of the Women's Faculty Club. In addition, Bryson was a Sterling Fellow at Yale University from 1927-1928, and from 1930-1931 she was head of residence at Berkeley's International House. In 1941, Bryson was a member of the U.S. Department's advisory committee on the adjustment of foreign students in the United States. Joining the Smith College faculty in 1931, Bryson served as both chairman of the Department of Sociology (starting in 1945) and as chairman of the Division of Social Sciences from 1948 until her death in 1952. During her employment at Smith, Bryson served on numerous committees and was the faculty resident of Lawrence House for many years. At the time of her death in 1952, Bryson was the Mary Huggins Gamble Professor of Sociology at Smith. Publishing many essays and books, Bryson authored one of her more well known works in 1945, titled: Man and Society: The Scottish Inquiry of the 18th Century. Upon the time of her death, she was working on a book regarding the foundations of American sociology. In addition to her numerous essays and books, Bryson contributed many articles to various encyclopedias and sociological journals. An internationally recognized sociologist and an active member of many sociological associations, Bryson was President of the Eastern Sociological Society from 1946 to 1947. Bryson died on December 18, 1952 in the college infirmary after a long illness.
Scope and Contents
Collection comprised of biographical information, correspondence, class materials, books and articles, including her 1927 article "The Comparable Interests of the Old Moral Philosophy and the Modern Social Sciences," published works by other intellectuals, including Edward Shils's 1948 book The Present State of American Sociology, and photographs.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Gladys Eugenia Bryson papers were donated to the Smith College Archives from a number of sources.
Bryson, Gladys Eugenia, 1894-1952
- Biographical Information, 1897-1953; undated (Box 690.1, Folder 1)
- Writings and Research Material, 1926-1953
  - Articles and book reviews, 1927-1952 (Box 690.1, Folder 2)
  - Becker, Howard: correspondence, 1951-1952 (Box 690.1, Folder 3)
  - "Conclusion" - various notes, 1948-1951 (Box 690.1, Folder 4)
  - "Continuation" - various notes, undated (Box 690.1, Folder 5)
  - "Frank Lester Ward" by Robert Raymond, 1951 (Box 690.1, Folder 6)
  - Journal articles, 1945-1952 (Box 690.1, Folder 7)
  - Methods bibliography, undated (Box 690.1, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous bibliography, undated (Box 690.1, Folder 9)
  - Notes, undated (Box 690.1, Folder 10)
  - Printed material and other writings, 1927 (Box 690.1, Folder 11)
  - Printed material and other writings, 1948; 1950 (Box 690.1, Folder 12)
  - Ross, Edward Alsworth: notes, 1938-1951 (Box 690.1, Folder 13)
  - Tawney and Montagne, undated (Box 690.2, Folder 1)
  - Writings, 1932-1939 (Box 690.2, Folder 2)
- Course Material, 1925-1950
  - 101T, 101H, 1925-1926 (Box 690.2, Folder 3)
  - Anthropology S185, undated (Box 690.2, Folder 4)
  - Geography, 1929 (Box 690.2, Folder 5)
  - Honors unit: Anthropology, 1950 (Box 690.2, Folder 6)
  - Morphopoulos 298a, 1928 (Box 690.2, Folder 7)
  - Political Science 298, 1926-1927 (Box 690.2, Folder 8)
  - Ritualism, 1928 (Box 690.2, Folder 9)
  - Seminar: Political Science 201, History of Political Thought, 1926-1927 (Box 690.2, Folder 10)
  - Seminar: Social Institutions, 1926 (Box 690.2, Folder 11)
  - Sociology 11b and 40b, includes bibliography, undated (Box 690.2, Folder 12)
  - Sociology 34: Expansion of Western Culture, honors exam, 1947 (Box 690.2, Folder 13)
  - Sociology 201b: Social Institutions, undated (Box 690.2, Folder 14)
  - Sociology 322b, undated (Box 690.2, Folder 15)
  - Social Evolution, 1927 (Box 690.2, Folder 16)
  - Social Psychology, 1926; undated (Box 690.2, Folder 17)
  - Berkeley, Sociology 121b: Social Institutions, 1926-1927 (Box 690.2, Folder 18)
  - Course listings from other schools, undated (Box 690.2, Folder 19)
  - Comprehensive bibliography and notes, undated (Box 690.3)